Guide to the Ethical Culture Fieldston School Records 1879-2017 MS 3042
New-York Historical Society
- Record Group 8. Alumni and alumni-relations (1891-2015; 28.5 linear feet), 216971; 28.5 Linear feet
  - Series I. Alumni Association, 1891-2001; 216972; 2 Linear feet
    - Constitutions and other papers, 1893-1905; 217154 (Offsite-box 91, Folder 3)
      Two copies of original Workingman's School Alumni Association constitutions, correspondence, ephemera, meeting materials.
    - Correspondence (14 folders), 1894-1937 (Offsite-box 91, Folder 4-17)
      Correspondence and related papers from the Alumni Association. Subject matter mostly involves membership, payment of dues, events (annual dinners, reunions, social dinners and dances), and coordination with the school and Ethical Culture Society. A large portion of correspondence is from the papers of Robert Eiserman, longtime secretary of the Association. This includes a small amount of correspondence with Felix Adler. Non-correspondence items include early copies of the Association's constitution, lists of members, membership applications, ephemera, and reports from the Association's Executive Committee or Treasurer. 1909 correspondence includes responses to an alumni questionnaire on the value of scholarships.
    - Minutes book, 1896-1899 (Offsite-box 91, Folder 18)
      Minutes written in notebook, with additional minutes, reports, and correspondence pasted onto pages. Includes reports from the treasurer and the Executive Committee.
    - Executive Committee - minutes book, 1896-1899 (Offsite-box 91, Folder 19)
      Meeting minutes, frequently discussing membership applications and resignations.
    - Record book, circa 1897 (Offsite-box 91, Folder 20)
      Notes on Alumni Association membership changes, 1896-1897, and partial lists of Workingman's School faculty, former pupils, graduates, and Alumni Association guests, 1887-1896.
    - Alumni Association - Class of 1930 (2 folders), 1933-1965 (Offsite-box 92, Folder 1-2)
      From papers of committee member Ira Oppenheimer. Primarily correspondence and class of 1930 questionnaire responses.
    - Executive Board - meeting minutes and related materials (5 folders), 1949-2000 (Offsite-box 92, Folder 3-7)
      Topics covered include fundraising, events, and college or career guidance. Related materials include lists of members, meeting materials, correspondence regarding nomination procedures.
    - Assorted correspondence and ephemera, 1950-2000 (Offsite-box 92, Folder 8)
    - Constitution revision and council structure, circa 1959 (Offsite-box 92, Folder 9)
      Correspondence and notes of Robert Eiserman, ephemera, meeting materials.
    - Alumni Association annual reports, 1960-1983 (Offsite-box 92, Folder 10)
    - Questionnaire mailings, circa 1966 (Offsite-box 92, Folder 11)
      Lists of responses (with addresses and some biographical information) from questionnaires for the classes of 1927 through 1933.
    - Art auction (2 folders), 1966-1968 (Offsite-box 92, Folder 12-13)
      Auction co-sponsored by Alumni Association. Ephemera, notes, lists of donors and items, and receipts.
    - Meeting materials and lists of members (2 folders), 1977-1985 (Offsite-box 92, Folder 14-15)
    - Executive Board, 1979 (Offsite-box 92, Folder 16)
      Meeting minutes and related documents on issue of the school's relationship to the Society and its use of public funds.
    - 50th reunions, 1979, 1985-1986 (Offsite-box 92, Folder 17)
      Notes and correspondence mostly from either Clarence (Clarry) Miller and Evelyn Rosenthal regarding the reunion of the class of 1929. Also includes attendance lists for reunions of classes of 1935 and 1936.
    - Miscellaneous, 1963-2001 (Offsite-box 92, Folder 18)
      Correspondence, ephemera, and lists.
    - Class lists - 1951, 1956, 1961, 1986 (Offsite-box 92, Folder 19)
  - Series II. Office of Alumni Affairs, 1926-2015; 216973; 12 Linear feet
    Series II contains records of the Ethical Culture Fieldston School's own work with alumni, through the Office of Alumni Affairs. Records were primarily created during the tenure of Director of Alumni Affairs Toby Himmel. Most of the material in this series relates to events (such as reunions, homecomings, and speaker series), alumni mentorship and diversity programs, and fund-raising. Records of the Office's work in establishing and maintaining a school archive, and tracking developments in the lives of alumni, are also found in this series.
    Subseries II.A: Alumni relations and school concerns
    Subseries II.B: Archives and alumni information
    - Subseries II.A. Alumni relations and school concerns, 1968-2015
      This subseries consists of records of the Office of Alumni Affairs and its work with alumni on events, programs, and development. It also contains records of the Office's work on other school business, such as communications, development, or technology projects.
      This subseries is arranged in alphabetical order (imposed by the archivist).
      - Admissions and registration (8 folders), 1992-2010 (Offsite-box 93, Folder 1-8)
        Reports from the Director of Admissions and Financial Aid. Ephemera, tour guide materials, materials for prospective parents, and alumni admissions event materials. (All materials involve general policies and statistics, with no information about specific students.)
      - Alumni Executive Board (5 folders), 1968-1999 (Offsite-box 93, Folder 9-13)
        Alumni Executive Board meeting records, member rosters, by-laws, and other materials. Most materials created after 1988.
      - Alumni relations - other institutions, 1993-2008 (Offsite-box 93, Folder 14)
        Ephemera and news clippings on alumni events or trends in alumni relations and independent schools.
      - Alumni survey - analysis of findings, 2005 (Offsite-box 93, Folder 15)
      - Board of Trustees (4 folders), 1995-2003 (Offsite-box 94, Folder 1-4)
        By-laws, meeting materials, correspondence, reports, lists of members.
      - Calendars (2 folders), 1989-2004 (Offsite-box 94, Folder 5-6)
        School calendars with notes by Toby Himmel.
      - Campus expansion plan (2 folders), 2003-2005 (Offsite-box 94, Folder 7-8)
      - Campus plaque audit, 1996-2002 (Offsite-box 94, Folder 9)
        Lists of, and policies for, plaques and named spaces.
      - Capital campaigns (3 folders), 1987-2003 (Offsite-box 94, Folder 10-12)
      - Class lists (2 folders), 2001-2003, 2013-2014 (Offsite-box 94, Folder 13-14)
        Lists of class placements and advisories.
      - Class newsletters (7 folders), 1993-2014 (Offsite-box 95, Folder 1-7)
        For classes of 1952, 1957, 1975, 1976, 1979, and 1980.
      - College preparation, 2004-2012 (Offsite-box 95, Folder 8)
        Includes copies of the Ethical Culture Fieldston School College Process Handbook.
      - Diversity and inclusion (5 folders), 1998-2008 (Offsite-box 95, Folder 9-13)
        Events such as Modified Awareness Day, Alumni of Color events, and speakers and retreats on the topic of diversity. Alumni mentorship programs. Records of the Multicultural Committee and the Alumni Multicultural Council.
      - Diversity and inclusion (3 folders), 2004-2015 (Offsite-box 96, Folder 1-3)
        Continued from above. Includes report "Diversity at ECF" by head of school Healey, 2004.
      - Ethics (3 folders), 2008-2011 (Offsite-box 96, Folder 4-6)
        Moral Leadership classes and the establishment of a new Ethics Fund.
      - Events (8 folders), 2001-2013 (Offsite-box 96, Folder 7-14)
        Materials related to Class Day, Founder's Day, Community Day, benefits, alumni panels and roundtables, talks, performances, memorials, and other events.
      - Events - Alumni documentary film series (3 folders), 2004 (Offsite-box 97, Folder 1-3)
        Alumni events with screenings of documentaries produced or directed by alumni.
      - Fieldston AlumNet information form (5 folders), undated (Offsite-box 97, Folder 4-8)
        Forms with contact information and areas of professional expertise.
      - Fieldston Enrichment Program, 1996-2003, 2013 (Offsite-box 97, Folder 9)
      - Graduating classes (4 folders), 2003-2010 (Offsite-box 97, Folder 10-13)
        Materials related to commencement, Kudos Day, senior dinner, senior gifts and related alumni events.
      - Graduating classes (3 folders), 2011-2013 (Offsite-box 98, Folder 1-3)
        Continued from above.
      - Graphic design, undated (Offsite-box 98, Folder 4)
      - Heads of school, 2009-2010 (Offsite-box 98, Folder 5)
      - Homecoming (7 folders), 2003, 2006-2014 (Offsite-box 98, Folder 6-12)
        Mostly ephemera and alumni sign in sheets. Some correspondence.
      - List of graduates working in education, 1978 (Offsite-box 98, Folder 13)
      - New York Association for Independent Schools (2 folders), 1990-1992 (Offsite-box 98, Folder 14-15)
      - New-York Historical Society photograph exhibition (3 folders), 2003-2004 (Offsite-box 99, Folder 1-3)
        Ephemera, correspondence, and other documents related to the New-York Society exhibition "From the Classroom to the World: Hine, Ulmann, Strand, Arbus and the Ethical Culture Fieldston School."
      - One hundred twenty-fifth anniversary (5 folders), 2000-2003 (Offsite-box 99, Folder 4-8)
      - Programs (5 folders), 1995-2010 (Offsite-box 99, Folder 9-13)
        Records relating to student and alumni programs. Examples include the Student Volunteer Club and the 2002 "alumni of color" dinner, and LGBTQ alumni programs.
      - Reunions (5 folders), 2011-2014 (Offsite-box 100, Folder 1-5)
        Ephemera, planning correspondence and documents (including copies of Reunion Committee Guidelines booklet).
      - Reunions and graduations (2 folders), 1971-1992 (Offsite-box 100, Folder 6-7)
        Ephemera and correspondence related to reunions, with photographs of 1987 San Diego reunion. Commencement ephemera and college lists for Fieldston graduates. Includes files from both the alumni and development departments.
      - Strategic planning (4 folders), 1993-2015 (Offsite-box 100, Folder 8-11)
        Includes materials on the Board of Governors 1993 retreat.
      - Strategic planning - communications (2 folders), 1998-2002 (Offsite-box 100, Folder 12-13)
      - Strategic planning - Communications and External Affairs Committee, 2000 (Offsite-box 101, Folder 1)
      - Strategic planning - development, 1988-2005 (Offsite-box 101, Folder 2)
      - Student directories (3 folders), 1974-1975, 1996-2002 (Offsite-box 101, Folder 3-5)
        Includes some staff directories and advisory lists.
      - Student and faculty directories (6 folders), 2002-2009 (Offsite-box 121, Folder 10-15)
        Directories published for families, with additions and other relevent materials added by Himmel.
      - Technology (3 folders), 1990-1997 (Offsite-box 101, Folder 6-8)
        Records related to database vendor and establishment of alumni website and email directory.
      - Toby Himmel administrative (3 folders), 1999-2013 (Offsite-box 101, Folder 9-11)
        Notes and resources for the Director of Alumni Relations, with drafts, notes, and correspondence relating to the 2013 strategic plan. Also records of tuition dates, and documents related to school accreditations.
      - Toby Himmel - various (2 folders), 1999-2015, undated (Offsite-box 42, Folder 20-21)
        Ephemera, news clippings, photographs, digital objects. Includes Best Software training guide, 2004.
      - Venture grants, 2002-2005 (Offsite-box 101, Folder 12)
    - Subseries II.B. Archives and alumni information, 1926-2014
      This subseries represents the Office of Alumni Affairs work with the Ethical Culture Fieldston School Archive, including responses to external requests for information about prominent alumni. It also contains news clippings and other sources of information on alumni and the school's history.
      - Alumni correspondence (2 folders), 2000-2011 (Offsite-box 101, Folder 13-14)
        Holiday cards, birth announcements, and other brief correspondence items from alumni.
      - Archives - inquiries (7 folders), 1995-2014 (Offsite-box 102, Folder 1-7)
        Inquiries into the use of the archive and photo archives, especially for research on specific notable alumni, with background materials collected by the alumni department. Primarily correspondence, news clippings, and copies of biographical information.
      - Archives - use and management (4 folders), 1975-2008 (Offsite-box 102, Folder 8-11)
        Copies of finding aid and other documents related to the school's archive. Resources on archives management, grant funding, and record retention schedules. Also includes copies of resources on school history, as well as a small amount of archival materials.
      - Archives planning and vendors (6 folders), 2004-2012 (Offsite-box 205, Folder 1-6)
      - Class of 1964 Archives Fund (4 folders), 2004-2014 (Offsite-box 205, Folder 7-10)
      - Archives projects (4 folders), 2003-2015 (Offsite-box 205, Folder 11-14)
      - Alumni collections (4 folders), 1978-2012 (Offsite-box 102, Folder 12-15)
        Assorted news clippings, photographs, ephemera, and correspondence from or relating to alumni or Ethical Culture Fieldston School history, collected by the Alumni Affairs department.
      - Annotated printed matter (3 folders), 1926-2000 (Offsite-box 103, Folder 1-3)
        Copies of alumni directories from 1986, 1994 and 2000; and 1926 Ethical Culture School Record, with notes and insertions.
      - Class of 1970 - civil rights (2 folders), 1963-2000 (Offsite-box 103, Folder 4-5)
        Ephemera and other archival materials, 1963-1970, related to student government and the Black and Latin American Students Club takeover of the administration building. Correspondence and reproductions of 1970 materials, circa 2000.
      - Ethical Culture Fieldston School history (6 folders), 1943-2007 (Offsite-box 103, Folder 6-11)
        Primarily news clippings and copies of resources on the history of the schools, collected by the Alumni Affairs department. Includes information on school songs. Also includes a small amount of ephemera and correspondence from 1960s and 1970s.
      - Staff memorials (2 folders), 1993-1998, 2003 (Offsite-box 103, Folder 12-13)
        Materials related to the memorials for Fieldston teachers including Earl Clemens, Renee Spodheim, and Magda Woss.
      - Milestones and deaths (2 folders), 2006-2011 (Offsite-box 103, Folder 14-15)
        News clippings and notes on deaths, marriages, and birth of children of alumni or former faculty.
      - Directories (4 folders), 1994-2002 (Offsite-box 205, Folder 15-18)
  - Series III. Alumni materials, 1892-2013; 216975; 14.5 Linear feet
    This series contains archival materials donated by, or related to, alumni. This includes student work, photographs, news clippings, and updates on the lives of various alumni after graduation. Materials were collected by individuals managing the Ethical Culture Fieldston School archive, the Office of Alumni Affairs, or the Alumni Association.
    Subseries III.A. Alumni archives contributions
    Subseries III.B. Alumni materials
    Subseries III.C. Mabel Towne Burnham
    - Subseries III.A. Alumni archives contributions, 1904-2013
      This subseries is made up of contributions to the archive from specific alumni. Types of materials include student work, ephemera, photographs, and reminiscences from alumni on their school experiences. Most contributions include some correspondence concerning the donation.
      This subseries is arranged in alphabetical order by last name, followed by contributions from various alumni. (Items compiled by the Ethical Culture Fieldston School, with order imposed by the archivist.)
      - Charles Stern Ascher (2 folders), 1909-1926 (Offsite-box 104, Folder 1-2)
        Schoolwork and ephemera from Charles Stern Ascher (class of 1914). Files also include biographical information on Ascher, and 2006 letter on donation from his granddaughter.
      - Charles Stern Ascher - student newspapers (2 folders), 1911-1913 (Offsite-box 104, Folder 3-4)
        Handwritten copies of The Beta Bazoo (1911-1912) and Gamma Gazette (1912-1913), periodicals produced by students including Ascher and Herbert Emmerich. (Original copy of The Beta Bazoo sealed for conservation - preservation photocopies of available for use by researchers.)
      - Henry Engle, 1921-1931, undated (Offsite-box 104, Folder 5)
        Photographs circa 1920s and 1930s, with photocopies of student materials. Also includes 2012 correspondence on donation.
      - Patt and Laurie Gibbs (8 folders), 1935-1949, 1959-1975 (Offsite-box 104, Folder 6-15)
        Contributions from Patt (Kook) Gibbs (class of 1949) and Laurie Gibbs (class of 1975). Student materials, such as ephemera, schoolwork and curriculum materials, 1930s-1970s. Alumni Association and parent materials 1960s-1970s.
      - Carol Warner Gluck - autograph book, 1927-1931 (Offsite-box 104, Folder 16)
        Notebook with messages and signatures from classmates.
      - Carol Warner Gluck (12 folders), 1946-1955, undated (Offsite-box 132, Folder 1-12)
        Teleplays and radio scripts by Carol Warner Gluck, Fieldston class of 1933. Files also include some short fiction and nonfiction writings, along with a small amount of proposals for series or correspondence. Some teleplays list station and air date, and several items stamped with "Blanche Gaines, Writers Representative." Folders are arranged in the order received.
      - Carol Warner Gluck (12 folders), 1949-1964, undated (Offsite-box 133, Folder 1-12)
      - Carol Warner Gluck (13 folders), 1953-1966, undated (Offsite-box 134, Folder 1-13)
      - Carol Warner Gluck (5 folders), 1953-1962, undated (Offsite-box 135, Folder 1-5)
      - Mildred Johnson, 1927, 1929 (Offsite-box 104, Folder 17)
        Two book covers, with handwritten notes ownership by Mildred Johnson.
      - Harriet Klein, 1937 (Offsite-box 104, Folder 18)
        Yearbook from the Department of Teacher Education, donated by Harriet (Levey) Klein (class of 1937), with 2010 note.
      - Belle Krasne Ribicoff, 1940-1942, 2013 (Offsite-box 104, Folder 19)
      - Robert Marshall (2 folders), 1928-1956 (Offsite-box 104, Folder 20-21)
        Published writings by Robert Marshall, with letter on donation by his brother, George Marshall.
      - Barbara Michaels - archival materials and notes (2 folders), 1921-1999 (Offsite-box 105, Folder 1-2)
        Files contain news clippings, photographs, and ephemera related to the schools, many with explanatory notes from Michaels (Fieldston alumna and daughter of Board member Nanette Rothschild).
      - Barbara Michaels - staff and alumni (2 folders), circa 1924-1931, 1961-2000 (Offsite-box 105, Folder 3-4)
        News clippings and other biographical materials relating to ECFS alumni and staff, including Victoria Wagner and Martha Munzer, with Michaels's explanatory notes.
      - Barbara Michaels - archives administration (2 folders), 1987-1990s (Offsite-box 105, Folder 5-6)
        Correspondence, notes, and other documents related to the establishment and use of the ECFS archives.
      - Jim (and Roy) Neuberger, 1946-1968, 2011 (Offsite-box 105, Folder 7)
        Society for Ethical Culture ephemera.
      - Various contributors (7 folders), 1904-2013, undated (Offsite-box 105, Folder 8-14)
        Ephemera, photographs, and examples of student work, donated to archive by alumni. Photographs are of students, graduations, reunions, a Fieldston baseball team, and the campus, some with identifying information. Includes some non-ECFS-related images donated by alumni (including photos of African-Americans apparently in the Jim Crow South from Bea Rosenblum, developed at Windmann Studios).
      - Various contributors (2 folders), 1921-2006 (Offsite-box 62, Folder 5-6)
      - Various contributors - reminiscences, 1990-2013, undated (Offsite-box 105, Folder 15)
        Correspondence with memories from various alumni. Includes a 1975 letter from Anna Kalshoven Graham (Mrs. William Ivers), student of the Workingman's School and 1908 graduate of the Normal Training Department. Also includes note from former Athletic Director Anton Smith.
      - Various contributors - later work (5 folders), 1974-2011 (Offsite-box 105, Folder 16-20)
        News clippings, correspondence, and other biographical information about various Fieldston alumni and their personal and professional accomplishments. Includes some obituaries and memorial materials.
    - Subseries III.B. Alumni biographies, 1912-1999
      This subseries consists of materials collected by alumni, the school, and the Alumni Association for the archive. Most of the subseries is made up of biographical alumni materials, along with reunion books of updates on the lives of alumni from certain Fieldston classes. It also includes some mid-twentieth century alumni-relations materials.
      This subseries is arranged in alphabetical order. (Items compiled by the Ethical Culture Fieldston School, with order imposed by the archivist.)
      - Alumni - biographical data - alphabetical (6 folders), 1912-1999 (Offsite-box 106, Folder 1-6)
        Files include notes, ephemera, news clippings, brief biographies, correspondence, and student work while at Fieldston. Type and volume of materials varies per person. Files for alumni Mischa Auer, Henry Dreyfuss, Rose Hannah Lewin Franken, Samuel Florman, Donald Harris, Lily Hayman, Michael Heidelberger, Alice Kahn Ladas, Joseph Mielziner, Howard Nemerov, Marie Neuberger, Hugh Nissenson, Robert Oppenheimer (3 folders), Gus Orstein, Gertrude Prince, Ithiel Pool, Richard Slobodin, and Paul Strand.
      - Alumni information cards, circa 1920s (Offsite-box 317)
        Name cards, some with address or other information, possibly for alumni. Some with years ranging from 1904-1926.
      - Alumni information cards, circa 1929 (Offsite-box 317)
        1 box of index cards, arranged by chronologically, with information including name, address, and occupation for alumni from classes 1903-1929.
      - Alumni information cards, circa mid-twentieth century (Offsite-box 316)
        3 boxes of index cards, arranged alphabetically, for alumni from the classes ranging from 1891-1942. All cards provide name, class, and contact information, with some cards providing information on colleges or universities attended, occupation, and marriage.
      - Alumni lists, 1930, 1964, 1978, 1981 (Offsite-box 106, Folder 7)
        List of alumni, list of college addresses, list of alumni publications, list of alumni families.
      - Alumni research project, 1959-1961 (Offsite-box 106, Folder 8)
        Study conducted during the tenure of Director Victoria Wagner. Includes copies of "Fieldston-Ethical Culture Schools Alumni Study: Comprehensive Report" and "Values and Attitudes: A Summary of Findings."
      - Alumni reunion books (6 folders), 1968-1997 (Offsite-box 106, Folder 9-14)
        Books of updates on members of classes of 1938, 1943, 1948, 1955, 1956, 1959, 1960, 1962-1967, 1975, 1977, and 1987. Reunion photographs for classes of 1955 and 1959.
      - Alumni reunion books (4 folders), 1972-1978 (Offsite-box 298, Folder 1-4)
        Alumni reunion books for the classes of 1947, 1948, 1948, 1950, 1952, 1959, 1963, 1964, and 1968.
      - Alumni update clippings (7 folders), 1981-1989 (Offsite-box 135, Folder 6-12)
        Primarily photographs, and clippings on alumni biographical updates from the ECS Reporter. Arranged chronologically by class year, from class of 1900 to class of 1989.
      - Articles and publications by alumni (2 folders), 1917-1978 (Offsite-box 106, Folder 15-16)
      - Class of 1947 50th reunion publication, 1997 (Offsite-box 273, Folder 3)